Guide to the Anson Phelps Stokes Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Journals, Speeches, Writings, and Research Materials, 1890-1958; PART I. II; 13.75 linear feet (35 boxes)
  - Books
    - Church and State in the United States
      - Typed draft (with notes for printer)
        - Book II, chapter XX, sections 6-11 (Box 165, Folder 198)
        - Book II, chapter XXI (Box 165, Folder 199)
        - Book II, chapter XXII (Box 165, Folder 200)
        - Book II, chapter XXIII (Box 166, Folder 201)
        - Book II, chapters XXIV-XXV (Box 166, Folder 202)
        - Book II, chapters XXVI-XXVII (Box 166, Folder 203)
        - Book II, chapter XXVIII, "Critical and Selected Bibliography (Box 166, Folder 204)
        - Book II, chapters XXIX-XXX, "Table of Dates," and "Appendices" (Box 166, Folder 205)
        - Addenda and Acknowledgments (Box 167, Folder 206)
        - Index (Box 167, Folder 207)
      - Introduction: Typed copy by Ralph H. Gabriel (Box 168, Folder 208)
      - Table of contents: Early outline, successive drafts, and final form, 1939-1950 (Box 168, Folder 209)
      - Illustrations: Lists, memorandum, and two political cartoons (Box 168, Folder 210)
      - Appendix (No. 6) and dust jacket (Box 168, Folder 211)
      - Memoranda re: proposed publication, tentative title page, proposed biography of APS for dust jacket, and outline of possible use of Church and State as basis for motion picture, 1945-1950 (Box 168, Folder 212)
      - Correspondence re: proposed outline and table of contents, 1938-1950 (Box 168, Folder 213)
      - Correspondence re: publication
        - Yale University Press, the Beacon Press, 1946-1948 (Box 168, Folder 214)
        - Macmillan Company, 1946 August - 1947 Oct; 1948 January - 1950 May (Box 168, Folder 215-216)
        - Harper Brothers, 1948 November - 1957 (Box 168, Folder 217-224)
      - Correspondence re: financial support
        - The Rockefeller Foundation, 1947-1950 (Box 168, Folder 225)
        - Everett R. Clinchy, 1948 (Box 168, Folder 226)
        - American Council of Learned Societies, 1948-1950 (Box 168, Folder 227)
        - Emory Ross, John R. Mott, Charles Clayton Morrison, the Cleveland H. Dodge Foundation, the James Stokes Society, and others, 1948-1950 (Box 168, Folder 228)
        - Old Dominion Foundation, 1950, 1951 June 6 (Box 168, Folder 229)
        - Report to the foundations, associations and individuals who aided publication, 1950 November - December (Box 168, Folder 230)
        - Memoranda re: expenses and financial support, 1948-1950 (Box 168, Folder 231)
        - Correspondence re: gift copies distributed by the Phelps-Stokes Fund and the United States Book Exchange, 1950-1955 (Box 168, Folder 232)
      - Copyright enquiries
        - Problems in obtaining permission for written material or illustrations, 1949-1950 (Box 168, Folder 233)
        - Lists indicating names of copyright holders to whom a form letter requesting permission to use material was sent; lists indicating which letters were unanswered, which permissions were given, 1949-1950 (Box 169, Folder 234)
        - Additional permissions required because of Stokes's modifications of the final chapter, 1949-1950 (Box 169, Folder 235)
        - Note cards of copyright holders who have granted permission, 1949-1950 (Box 169, Folder 236)
        - Note cards of copyright holders who have not replied to letter of APS, 1949-1950 (Box 169, Folder 237)
      - Copyright replies: Letters giving permission to publish copyrighted material with acknowledgments, 1949-1950
        - A-B (Box 169, Folder 238)
        - C (Box 169, Folder 239)
        - D-K (Box 169, Folder 240)
        - L-N (Box 169, Folder 241)
        - O-S (Box 169, Folder 242)
        - T-Z (Box 169, Folder 243)
        - Re: illustrations, A-Z (Box 169, Folder 244)
      - Correspondence re: illustrations
        - 1939 Dec 20; 1940 Dec 12; 1949 Jun - 1950 Feb (Box 169, Folder 245-248)
      - Correspondence with proofreader
        See: H. Robinson Shipherd, Part I, box 123, folder 2211
      - Correspondence re: reading of manuscript
        See: William Warren Sweet, Part I, box 125, folder 2239
      - General correspondence relating to book, 1948-1953 (Box 169, Folder 249-250)
      - Additional correspondence related to Church and State
        See: Part I, Series I: John D. Rockefeller See: Part I, Series I: Winifred E. Garrison See: Part I, Series I: Evarts Greene See: Part I, Series I: Helen Reed See: Part I, Series I: Carl Rollins
      - Pre-publication publicity: Harpers Brothers catalogue, pamphlets (Box 169, Folder 251)
      - Post-publication publicity: circular, and list of those to receive announcement of publication, Circa 1950 (Box 169, Folder 252)
      - Post-publication publicity: circulars, abstracts from reviews, and advertisements, 1950-1951 (Box 169, Folder 253)
      - Lists: people to receive complimentary copies, English agents of Harper Brothers (Box 169, Folder 254)
      - Reception in honor of publication: correspondence, telegrams, photographs, press releases, and inscriptions for gift copies, 1950 May 10 (Box 169, Folder 255)
      - Correspondence, comments, congratulations, and acknowledgments of complimentary copies, A-Z, 1950-1951 (Box 169, Folder 256)
      - Resolutions honoring APS by Yale University, Washington Cathedral, and Trinity Church, Lenox, 1950 May (Box 169, Folder 257)
      - Book Reviews (by periodical)
        - A-B (by periodical), 1950-1952 (Box 170, Folder 258)
        - C, 1950-1952 (Box 170, Folder 259)
        - D-G, 1950-1952 (Box 170, Folder 260)
        - H-M, 1950-1952 (Box 170, Folder 261)
        - N-Z, 1950-1952 (Box 170, Folder 262)
        - Quotations from reviews, 1950-1951 (Box 170, Folder 263)
        - Printed material mentioning APS and Church and State in the United States, 1950-1952 (Box 170, Folder 264)
        - Revised edition, reviews and publicity, 1964-1965 (Box 170, Folder 265)
        - Outline of proposed scrap book (Box 170, Folder 266)
      - Research material
        - Correspondence, A-B, 1937-1949 (Box 170, Folder 267)
        - Research correspondence
          See: Ellen C. Ahern, Part I, box 99, folders 1620-1621
        - Correspondence, C-D, 1937-1949 (Box 170, Folder 268)
        - Correspondence, E-G, 1937-1949 (Box 170, Folder 269)
        - Correspondence, H-L, 1937-1949 (Box 170, Folder 270)
        - Correspondence, M-R, 1937-1949 (Box 170, Folder 271)
        - Correspondence, S-Z, unidentified, 1937-1949 (Box 170, Folder 272)
        - Census of Religious Bodies (Box 171, Folder 273)
        - Chaplaincy I (includes correspondence) (Box 171, Folder 274)
        - Chaplaincy II (includes correspondence) (Box 171, Folder 275)
        - Chaplaincy III (includes correspondence) (Box 171, Folder 276)
        - Chaplaincy IV (includes correspondence) (Box 171, Folder 277)
        - Church-State history (Box 171, Folder 278)
        - Church-State thought (Box 171, Folder 279)
        - Conscription (includes correspondence) (Box 171, Folder 280)
        - Courts I (Box 171, Folder 281)
        - Courts II (includes correspondence) (Box 171, Folder 282)
        - Ecumenicalism and inter-faith cooperation (Box 171, Folder 283)
        - Education: Academic freedom (Box 171, Folder 284)
        - Education: The Amish (Box 171, Folder 285)
        - Education: Church-related schools (includes correspondence) (Box 171, Folder 286)
        - Education: National Education Association (Box 171, Folder 287)
        - Education: Public and parochial schools (Box 172, Folder 288)
        - Education: Public universities (includes correspondence) (Box 172, Folder 289)
        - Education: Religion and public schools, I (Box 172, Folder 290)
        - Education: Religion and public schools, II (includes correspondence) (Box 172, Folder 291)
        - Education: Religious education (Box 172, Folder 292)
        - Foreign Aid (Box 172, Folder 293)
        - Freedom of religion I (includes correspondence) (Box 172, Folder 294)
        - Freedom of religion II (includes correspondence) (Box 172, Folder 295)
        - Freedom of religion and the law I (Box 172, Folder 296)
        - Freedom of religion and the law II (Box 172, Folder 297)
        - Jehovah's Witnesses (Box 172, Folder 298)
        - Labor (Box 172, Folder 299)
        - Legislation (Box 172, Folder 300)
        - Marriage and birth control (Box 173, Folder 301)
        - Minority rights (includes correspondence) (Box 173, Folder 302)
        - National anniversaries (includes correspondence) (Box 173, Folder 303)
        - New Deal (includes WPA correspondence) (Box 173, Folder 304)
        - Peace (includes correspondence) (Box 173, Folder 305)
        - Proclamations and memorials (Box 173, Folder 306)
        - Radio: Issues in access and broadcasting (Box 173, Folder 307)
        - Religion in government (Box 173, Folder 308)
        - Roman Catholic-Protestant conflicts (Box 173, Folder 309)
        - Race (Box 173, Folder 310)
        - Social ideals and objectives (Box 173, Folder 311)
        - Social Security (Box 173, Folder 312)
        - United Service Organizations (Box 173, Folder 313)
        - The Vatican, U.S. ambassador to (Box 173, Folder 314)
        - War Relief (includes correspondence) (Box 174, Folder 315)
        - World War II (Box 174, Folder 316-317)
        - Miscellaneous I-IV (Box 174, Folder 318-321)
        - Material collected for second edition of Church and State (Box 174, Folder 322)
- Subjects File, 1767-(1900-1958); PART I. III; 8 linear feet (20 boxes)
  In Part I, Series III the material is grouped by subject: an institution, organization, or project in which Stokes was involved. The twelve subjects, in alphabetical order, are: African Tour, 1932-1933; The Brookings Institution; General and International Education Boards; Phelps Stokes Fund; Refugee Relief; Reorganization of the Federal Judiciary; St. Paul's School; Washington Cathedral; Washington, D.C., Committees; Yale-in-China; Yale-New Haven History; and Yale, the Portsmouth Treaty, and Japan.
  Within a subject, items may be filed in chronological order or arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  - African Tour, 1932-1933
    - Agendas, itineraries, and programs, 1932-1934 (Box 175, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence re: travel arrangements and permits, 1932 April - November (Box 175, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence re: shipping arrangements for African purchases, 1932 November - 1933 June (Box 175, Folder 3)
    - Expense account of Anson Phelps Stokes as Visiting Carnegie Lecturer to Africa, 1932 (Box 175, Folder 4)
    - Memoranda, undated (Box 175, Folder 5)
    - Newsletters from Anson Phelps Stokes to friends in the United States, 1932 August - December (Box 175, Folder 6)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1932-1933 (Box 175, Folder 7)
    - Recommendations and commitments made by Stokes during his African tour and a list of people met and their addresses, 1932-1933 (Box 175, Folder 8)
    - Report of Anson Phelps Stokes on education, native welfare and race relations in East and South Africa, issued by the Carnegie Corporation, 1934 February (Box 175, Folder 9)
    - Report of Anson Phelps Stokes on education, native welfare and race relations in East and South Africa; comments from persons who received copies, 1934 April - December (Box 175, Folder 10)
  - The Brookings Institution
    - Certificate of incorporation and by-laws (copies), 1927 December 3; 1937 May 7; 1939 April 26; (1941?) (Box 175, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence, minutes of the meetings of the trustees, memoranda, and reports, 1935-1946 (Box 175, Folder 12-17)
    - Correspondence of Anson Phelps Stokes and Isabel V. and Robert S. Brookings
      See: Part I, Series I
    - List of publications of the Brookings Institution, 1935 (Box 175, Folder 18)
    - Newspaper article on capitalism by Robert S. Brookings, 1931 March 1 (Box 175, Folder 19)
    - Pamphlets on the Brookings Institution, its organization and activities, 1935-1946 (Box 175, Folder 20)
  - General and International Education Boards
    - Minutes of the organizational meeting of the American University Union in Europe, with a copy of the constitution, 1917 July 6 (Box 176, Folder 21)
    - Minutes of trustees' meetings and reports of the American University Union in Europe, 1920-1921, 1923 (Box 176, Folder 22)
    - Correspondence of Anson Phelps Stokes with the American University Union and the American Council on Education, 1920-1929 (Box 176, Folder 23)
    - Bulletins, reports and copies of fellowship applications of the Institute of International Education, 1921-1925 (Box 176, Folder 24)
    - Memorandum by John D. Rockefeller, Jr. re: an executive secretary for the Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial Fund, 1921 April 14 (Box 176, Folder 25)
    - Proposed amended by-laws of the General Education Board, 1922 (Box 176, Folder 26)
    - Minutes of an informal conference between representatives of the Institute of International Education and the American University Union in Europe, (1923?) September 17 (Box 176, Folder 27)
    - Statement of general purposes of the International Education Board, 1924 October 30 (Box 176, Folder 28)
    - Agenda, minutes, and reports of the meetings of the Committee on the American University Union of the American Council on Education, 1924-1927 (Box 176, Folder 29)
    - Agenda, minutes, and reports of the meetings of the Executive Committee of the American Council on Education, 1924-1929 (Box 176, Folder 30)
    - Agenda, minutes, and reports of meetings of the Administrative Board of the Institute of International Education, 1924-1931 (Box 176, Folder 31)
    - Data on institutions and associations affiliated with the American Council on Education, Circa 1925 (Box 176, Folder 32)
    - Memoranda by Anson Phelps Stokes and others on centers of international cooperation, 1925, undated (Box 176, Folder 33)
    - Pamphlets and bulletins of the American University Union and the Institute of International Education, 1925-1931, 1949, undated (Box 176, Folder 34)
    - Correspondence of Anson Phelps Stokes and the Institute of International Education, 1926-1932 (Box 176, Folder 35)
    - Tentative recommendations for reorganizing the international educational work of the Institute of International Education, the American Council on Education, and the American University Union, 1926 December 15 (Box 176, Folder 36)
    - Correspondence of Anson Phelps Stokes and fellow members of the committee on reorganization of the General Education Board, 1926 December - 1927 February (Box 176, Folder 37)
    - Minutes of meetings of the General Education Board (fragment for 1930), 1927 November 17; December 19; 1930 October 17 (Box 176, Folder 38)
    - Agenda, minutes and reports of the meetings of the Committee on the American University Union of the Institute of International Education, 1928-1939 (Box 176, Folder 39)
    - Tribute to Dr. Edwin Anderson Alderman upon his retirement from the General Education Board (probably written by APS), (1929) (Box 176, Folder 40)
    - Remarks by John D. Rockefeller, Jr., on Dr. Vincent's service as President of the Rockefeller Foundation, 1929 November 13 (Box 176, Folder 41)
    - Tribute to Dr. George Edgar Vincent upon his retirement from the General Education Board (probably written by APS), (1930) (Box 176, Folder 42)
    - Tribute to Dr. Albert Shaw upon his retirement from the General Education Board (probably written by APS), (1930) (Box 176, Folder 43)
    - Excerpt from the minutes of the Rockefeller Foundation recording the resignation of Anson Phelps Stokes, 1932 April 13 (Box 176, Folder 44)
    - Remarks of the retiring chairman, Mr. John D. Rockefeller, Jr., at the meeting of the General Education Board, 1939 April 6 (Box 176, Folder 45)
    - Correspondence of Anson Phelps Stokes with the American University Union and the American Council on Education, 1930-1938 (Box 176, Folder 46)
    - Agenda, minutes and reports of the meetings of the Committee on the American University Union of the Institute of International Education, 1940-1946 (Box 176, Folder 47)
    - Diagram indicating funding of the General Education Board, undated (Box 176, Folder 48)
  - Phelps-Stokes Fund (Subject file contains three W.E.B. DuBois letters)
    - Minutes and financial records
      - Fifteen-Year Financial Report, 1913-1927 (Box 177, Folder 49)
      - Minutes of meetings of the trustees, 1923-1926 (Box 177, Folder 50)
      - Minutes of a meeting of the Educational Committee, 1925 April 23 (Box 177, Folder 51)
      - Resolutions submitted to the trustees by APS and others, 1925, 1938-1943 (Box 177, Folder 52)
      - Trustees' report on examination of accounts, 1926 November 15 (Box 177, Folder 53)
      - Minutes of a meeting of the Committee on Education, 1927 November 3 (Box 177, Folder 54)
      - Minutes of meetings of the trustees, 1927-1928 (Box 177, Folder 55)
      - Budget proposals, 1928-1930 (Box 177, Folder 56)
      - Minutes of meetings of the trustees, 1929 (Box 177, Folder 57)
      - Minutes of meetings of the Executive Committee and the trustees, 1930-1931 (Box 177, Folder 58)
      - Budget proposals, 1930-1932 (Box 177, Folder 59)
      - Minutes of meetings of the trustees, 1932-1935 (Box 177, Folder 60-61)
      - Treasurer's report, 1934 November 15 - 1935 April 15 (Box 177, Folder 62)
      - Minutes of meetings of the trustees, 1936-1938 (Box 177, Folder 63-65)
      - Minutes of meetings of the Finance Committee, 1938 April 20, November 23 (Box 177, Folder 66)
      - Budget proposals, estimated income and balances, 1938-1939 (Box 177, Folder 67)
      - Minutes of meetings of the trustees, 1939 (Box 177, Folder 68)
      - Minutes of a meeting of the Housing Committee, 1939 February 17 (Box 177, Folder 69)
      - Minutes of meetings of the trustees, 1940 (Box 178, Folder 70)
      - Summary of investments, 1940 (Box 178, Folder 71)
      - Budget proposals for the fiscal year ending October 31, 1941, 1940 (Box 178, Folder 72)
      - Summary of investments and memoranda to members of the Finance Committee, 1941 (Box 178, Folder 73)
      - Budget proposals for the fiscal year ending October 31, 1942, 1941 November 12 (Box 178, Folder 74)
      - Minutes of meetings of the trustees, 1941-1942 (Box 178, Folder 75)
      - Budget proposals for the fiscal year ending October 31, 1944, 1943 November 6 (Box 178, Folder 76)
      - Minutes of a conference between the trustees of the Phelps-Stokes Fund and the Association to Promote Better Housing for Girls, Inc., 1943 December 2 (Box 178, Folder 77)
      - Minutes of meetings of the trustees, 1943-1944 (Box 178, Folder 78)
      - Minutes of meetings of the Committee on Phelps-Stokes Fund policy, 1944 July 25, December 27 (Box 178, Folder 79)
      - Budget proposals for the fiscal year ending October 31, 1946, 1945 November 14 (Box 178, Folder 80)
      - Minutes of meetings of the trustees, 1945-1946 (Box 178, Folder 81)
      - Summary of investments, 1946 October 31 (Box 178, Folder 82)
      - Minutes of meetings of the trustees, 1947-1949 (Box 178, Folder 83-84)
      - Summary of investments, 1950 October 31 (Box 178, Folder 85)
    - Correspondence
      - Official correspondence of APS: notices to trustees, agenda of meetings, telegrams, 1924-1945 (Box 178, Folder 86-88)
      - Official correspondence of APS: notices to trustees, agenda of meetings, telegrams, 1946 (Box 179, Folder 89)
      - Correspondence of APS and Fund officers: notices to trustees, agenda of meetings, telegrams, 1947-1950; 1956-1957 (Box 179, Folder 90-91)
      - Correspondence of APS, President of the Phelps-Stokes Fund, and O.J.S. Satchel, Secretary of the J.W. Jagger Bequest for the teaching of English in the Union of South Africa, 1936 February 14; March 20 (Box 179, Folder 92)
      - Address book with listings from the Phelps-Stokes Fund Office, 1947 (Box 179, Folder 93)
      - Reports, memoranda and public statements
      - Extract from the will of Caroline Phelps Stokes, Act of Incorporation of the Phelps-Stokes Fund Trustees, and By-Laws of the Trustees, reprinted from the Twenty-Year Report of the Phelps-Stokes Fund, 1911-1931 (Box 179, Folder 94)
      - Memoranda by APS and others, 1922-1947 (Box 179, Folder 95)
      - Statement by the Secretary of the Phelps-Stokes Fund, Anson Phelps Stokes, re: Carter Woodson's attacks on Dr. Thomas Jesse Jones, 1924 March 12 (Box 179, Folder 96)
      - Statements regarding the organization, policy and activities of the Phelps-Stokes Fund, 1925, 1926 (Box 179, Folder 97)
      - Report on the Jeanes Visiting Teachers Abroad by Thomas Jesse Jones, 1933 April 10 (Box 179, Folder 98)
      - "A Brief Summary of the Current Educational Activities of the Phelps-Stokes Fund" by Thomas Jesse Jones, 1943 April (Box 179, Folder 99)
      - Press releases, 1945-1949 (Box 179, Folder 100)
      - "A Brief Summary of the Services Rendered by Dr. Anson Phelps Stokes as a Trustee and Officer of the Phelps-Stokes Fund", 1946 April 17 (Box 179, Folder 101)
      - Reports by Anson Phelps Stokes, Dr. Jackson Davis, and Dr. Channing Tobias at the meeting of the trustees, 1946 November 19 (Box 179, Folder 102)
      - Report of the Director, Channing H. Tobias, to the trustees, 1947 November 19 (Box 179, Folder 103)
      - Report of the program for the training of the Negro rural ministry, 1949 May 31 (Box 179, Folder 104)
      - Report and memorandum of the special committee on important projects in American-African relations, 1949 November (Box 179, Folder 105)
      - Confidential report to the Board of Trustees on interviews and correspondence bearing upon the proposed study of Christian missions in a changing Africa by Channing H. Tobias, 1950 October (Box 179, Folder 106)
    - Projects and special events
      - Low income housing projects: Clipping describing model tenement plan of the Phelps-Stokes Fund in the New York Evening Post, 1922 March 25 (Box 179, Folder 107)
      - Low income housing projects: Description of an architectural competition sponsored by the Phelps-Stokes Fund, 1933 April 22 (Box 179, Folder 108)
      - Low income housing projects: Changes recommended by the trustees of the Fund in a Congressional housing bill, 1937 April 21 (Box 179, Folder 109)
      - Commission to East Africa: "East Africa and Education," draft of a speech by Thomas Jesse Jones at a dinner given by the British Government, 1925 March 26 (Box 179, Folder 110)
      - Commission to East Africa: News clippings about the British Government's tribute to Thomas Jesse Jones, 1925 March (Box 179, Folder 111)
      - Commission to East Africa: Review of "Education in East Africa," a report by Thomas Jesse Jones, by P.W. Wilson in the New York Times Book Review, 1925 May 24 (Box 179, Folder 112)
      - Commission to East Africa: Pamphlets on the commission and Education in East Africa, Circa 1925 (Box 179, Folder 113)
      - Phelps-Stokes Fund dinner in honor of C.T. Loram: Address by Dr. Loram, Native Affairs Commissioner of the Union of South Africa, 1926 October 25 (Box 179, Folder 114)
      - African students in the U.S.A.: Tentative memorandum by APS for African students, with comments and criticisms by others, 1929 May (Box 179, Folder 115)
      - African students in the U.S.A.: Final form of Phelps-Stokes Fund memorandum offering information and advice to African students, 1929 June 1 (Box 179, Folder 116)
      - African students in the U.S.A.: Correspondence of APS re: efforts to distribute the Phelps-Stokes Fund memorandum to all U.S. consular offices in Africa, 1929 June - 1930 April (Box 179, Folder 117)
      - African students in the U.S.A.: Revised memorandum of the Phelps-Stokes Fund for African students, 1934 June 1 (Box 179, Folder 118)